# Saskia Nowicki

Research Associate, Environmental Systems Science for Policy Geography and the Environment · University of Oxford · S Parks Road OX1 3QY, UK ☑ saskia.nowicki@ouce.ox.ac.uk +44 7464 753326 saskia-nowicki.github.io

## Overview

As a social-ecological systems specialist, I do solution-focused research that cuts across natural, social, and health sciences to respond to long-standing and emerging water quality risks. I work collaboratively with interdisciplinary research teams and with partners beyond academia to co-produce insight that supports just transitions for healthy freshwater ecosystems and equitable safe water service delivery.

# **Employment**

Smith School of Enterprise and the Environment, University of Oxford Research associate Research assistant	Oxford, UK 06/2021 - present 09/2016 - 2018
School of Geography and the Environment, University of Oxford Casual lecturer Teaching assistant	Oxford, UK 09/2021 - present 09/2018 - 2021
Dept for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs, Central Science Division Policy secondment, One Health governance strategy	London, UK 10/2022 - 03/2023
Dept of Earth Sciences, University of Oxford Tutor, Myanmar TIDE Programme	Oxford, UK 04/2019 - 2020
Oxford Policy Management, WASH Team Consultant	Oxford, UK 09/2016 - 01/2017
SRK Consulting, Geochemistry Team Consultant	Vancouver, Canada $06/2012$ - $2015$
Gregory-Eaves Limnology Lab, McGill University Research assistant	Montreal, Canada 2011
Education	
University of Oxford, DPhil Water and Health	2017 - 2021

First class honours, distinction

Thesis: Data, Decisions, & Drinking-Water Safety [view]

University of Oxford, MSc Water Science, Policy and Management Thesis: Variability in Drinking-water Microbial Contamination Risk Top of class, distinction	2015 - 2016
McGill University, BSc (Hons) Environmental Science Concentration: Water Environments and Ecosystems, Biological Stream	2008 - 2012

### Selected Publications

(2024) Reinforcing feedbacks for sustainable implementation of rural drinking-water treatment technology.  $ACS\ ES\&T\ Water$ . Laauwen M & Nowicki S. [view]

(2023) Water chemistry poses health risks as reliance on groundwater increases: a systematic review of hydrogeochemistry research from Ethiopia and Kenya. *STOTEN*. **Nowicki S**, Birhanu B, Tanui F, Sule MN, Charles K, Olago D, & Kebede S. [view]

(2023) Results-based funding for safe drinking water services: How a standard contract design with payment for results can accelerate safe drinking water services at scale. REACH working paper 13. University of Oxford and Uptime Global. Oxford, UK. [view]

(2022) Fear, efficacy, and environmental health risk reporting: complex responses to water quality test results in low-income communities. *IJERPH*. **Nowicki S**, Bukachi S, Hoque S, Katuva J, Musyoka M, Sammy M, Mwaniki M, Omia D, Wambua F, & Charles, K. [view]

(2021) The utility of *Escherichia coli* as a contamination indicator for rural drinking water: evidence from whole genome sequencing. *PLoS ONE*. **Nowicki S**, deLaurent ZR, de Villiers EP, Githinji G, & Charles KJ. [view]

(2021) Global prospects to deliver safe drinking water services for 100 million rural people by 2030. REACH Working Paper 12. RWSN and University of Oxford. Oxford, UK. [view]

(2020) Including water quality monitoring in rural water services: why safe water requires challenging the quantity versus quality dichotomy. *npj Clean Water*. **Nowicki S**, Koehler J, & Charles KJ. [view]

(2020) A framework for monitoring the safety of water services: from measurements to security. *npj* Clean Water. Charles KJ, **Nowicki S**, & Bartram JK. [view]

(2019) Tryptophan-like fluorescence as a measure of microbial contamination risk in groundwater. STOTEN. Nowicki S, Lapworth DJ, Ward JST, Thomson P, & Charles K. [view]

### **Funding**

Grants	
Africa Oxford Catalyst Grant (Co-I, coordinated the application)	£3500 [2024]
UKRI MRC PHIND Grant (Co-I, led the application)	£150,000 [2023-24]
SoGE Research Environment and Culture Fund (led)	£1,000 [2023]
ESRC IAA Grant Stages 1, 2, 3 (Co-I, co-wrote the applications)	£35,000 [2020-23]
SoGE Engagement and Impact Inspiration Fund Grant (led)	£1,000 [2016]
Canada NSERC Undergraduate Research Grant (led)	\$6,000 [2011]
Awards	
SoGE ECR Engagement and Impact Award	£500 [2022]
McGill University Davidovic Field Study Award	£ $1000$ [ $2011$ ]
Scholarships	
Commonwealth Scholarship for Doctoral Study in the UK	£100,000 [2017-20]
Linacre Canadian National Scholarship & SoGE Departmental Scholarship	£10,000 [2015-16]